Finding Aid for Hal Butler papers, 1930-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hal Butler papers
1930-2006
Butler, Hal.
2009042 Aa 2
Detroit-based editor, pulp fiction writer, novelist, nonfiction author, and freelance travel writer; collection contains background materials and extensive business files which include correspondence, contracts, copyrights, photographs, and a wide range of publications.
6 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Joyce Butler Musto (donor no. 10068 ) in several accessions, 2008-2009.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Harold Charles "Hal" Butler was a professional man of letters; over the course of his career, he was a reporter, editor, pulp fiction writer, novelist, nonfiction author, and freelance travel writer. He was born in St. Louis, MO on January 3, 1913 and in 1916 his family moved to Detroit where Butler embarked upon his career by creating 'books' of short stories as a precocious 10 year old. He was a reporter for the school paper at Detroit's Central High School and after graduation he attended night school and took correspondence courses in writing and journalism. His first job was in the correspondence department of the Detroit City Gas Company after which he worked in the purchasing department of the Ford Motor Company. From this position, he advanced himself to write for various company publications, including the employee newspaper Rouge News (which became Ford World), Ford Dealer Magazine, and the leisure and travel magazine Ford Times. Butler served as managing editor of the latter publication for ten years until his retirement in 1974.
In addition to his professional obligations at Ford, Butler wrote assiduously in a variety of genres for a great many publications. In 1991, he estimated that he had written over one hundred magazine articles and a comparable number of newspaper features. He began his freelance career writing sports and detective stories for pulp magazines, the first of which was published in 1945 in Thrilling Detective magazine. As the market for pulp fiction dwindled in the fifties, Butler turned to nonfiction writing and found outlets in popular men's magazines as well as such mainstream publications as the Saturday Evening Post and American Mercury. Through the late sixties and seventies Butler wrote twelve sports-related books for juvenile readers as well as four nonfiction works for adults. In 1981, he published an historical romance novel under the pen name "Beverly Butler." Following his retirement, Butler traveled extensively and the majority of his work from the seventies and eighties consisted of freelance travel pieces. Near the end of his career, he returned to fiction and wrote two unpublished novels, Copper Fever! and Murder in the Tropics, of which only the former survives.
Butler was married to Eleanor Elizabeth (Davis) on August 20, 1938 at Mt. Hope Congregational Church in Detroit and they lived happily together until his death. The Butlers lived in the Detroit area with their two daughters, Beverly Alice (1940-1981) and Joyce Diane (Musto) (b. 1943) and summered at their family retreat in northwestern Michigan. Hal Butler passed away on June 16, 2002 in Southfield, MI.
The Hal Butler papers reflect the versatility, industry, and imagination of their creator's mind. Throughout his career as a writer and editor for the Ford Motor Company, Butler never ceased to follow his passion for describing his travels and telling tales of sports, mystery, and adventure. This collection will be of value to those interested in travel writing, the Great Lakes region, and publishing genres such as pulp fiction and 1950's men's magazines.
Subjects:
Adventure stories, American.; Authors and publishers--United States.; Butler, Eleanor.; Butler, Hal.; Editors--United States.; Freelance journalism.; Journalists--United States.; Sports journalism--Authorship.; Travel writing.; Zeta Tau Alpha. Mothers Club of Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Allison, Bob, 1934-1995; Butler, Hal.; Baseball players--United States.; Cash, Norman, 1934-; Detroit Zoological Park (Mich.); Dancers--United States.; Freedom Train.; Horton, Willie, 1942-; Kaline, Albert William, 1934-; Killebrew, Harmon Clayton, 1936-; Showgirls--United States.; Stunyo, Jeanne.; Trains--United States.; Zoos--Michigan--Detroit.
Contributors
Butler, Eleanor.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Personal
  The Personal series contains information about Hal Butler and his wife Eleanor. It includes biographical sketches, obituaries, clippings, and photographs.
  - Background Information
    - Butler, Eleanor Elizabeth (Davis), 2006 (Box 1)
    - Butler, Hal, 1990-2002 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1964-2002 (Box 1)
  - Notebooks, 1990s (Box 1)
    (descriptions of photographs taken on various trips)
  - Photographs
    - Butler, Eleanor: various, undated, 1953 (Box 1)
    - Butler Family, circa 1960 (Box 1)
    - Butler, Hal
      - circa 1940s, 1963 (Box 1)
      - Aboard U.S. Freedom Train, circa 1947-1948 (Box 1)
      - Receiving Baltimore city key, circa 1967-1971 (Box 1)
      - With Jack Webb, 1955 (Box 1)
      - Various, 1953-1963 (Box 1)
    - Butler, Hal and Eleanor
      - Caribbean Cruise, 1990 (Box 1)
        (includes notes)
      - European Vacation, circa 1950s (Box 1)
      - On board Q.T.E.V. "Queen of Bermuda", 1956 (Box 1)
      - Various, 1960s-1990s (Box 1)
    - Chicago Bike Hike, 1971 (Box 1)
- Business
  The Business series documents the professional aspects of Hal Butler's career with publishing contracts, copyright records, correspondence, royalty statements, reviews, and a range of photographs (including shots of Butler with Baseball Hall of Fame members Harmon Killebrew and Al Kaline). It contains an index of articles written by Butler from 1939-1974 as well as a catalog of book profits tallied in the 1980s.
  - Book Profits, circa 1980s (Box 1)
  - Contracts, 1965-1981 (Box 1)
  - Copyright Records, 1966-1980 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1965-1992; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - First payment as an author, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Index of Articles, 1939-1974 (Box 1)
  - Reviews and Related Materials
    - Abandon Ship!, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Baseball's Champion Pitchers, 1975 (Box 1)
    - The Harmon Killebrew Story, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Inferno!, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Magnolia Plantation, circa 1980; 1981 (Box 1)
    - Stormin' Norman Cash, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Other, 1968-1976 (Box 1)
  - Records of all publications, 1946-1990 (Box 1)
  - Royalty Statements, 1966-1984; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Abandon Ship!, circa 1974 (Box 1)
    - Acapulco, undated (Box 1)
    - Allison, Bob, circa 1967 (Box 1)
    - Cash, Norman, circa 1967 (Box 1)
    - Detroit Zoo, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - European Sites, undated (Box 1)
    - Ford Train (with Hal Butler), circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Grindstone City, circa 1960s (Box 1)
      (includes photos of Eleanor Butler)
    - Horton, Willie, circa 1970 (Box 1)
    - Kaline, Al, circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Kaline, Al, circa 1973 (Box 1)
    - Killebrew, Harmon, circa 1965 (Box 1)
    - The MacArthur Memorial, undated (Box 1)
    - Nature at War, circa 1976 (Box 1)
    - Norfolk, VA, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Showgirls (unidentified), undated (Box 1)
    - Springfield, IL (Lincoln Heritage Trail), undated (Box 1)
    - Stunyo, Jeanne, circa 1956 (Box 1)
      (1956 Olympic silver medallist on the three-meter springboard)
    - "Texas" (musical drama), undated (Box 1)
    - There's Nothing New in Sports, circa 1967 (Box 1)
    - Various stock photos, undated (Box 1)
- Writings
  The Writings series documents Butler's output in six distinct subseries. "Manuscripts" includes the unpublished novel Copper Fever! as well as the drafts of various travel articles. "Books" includes 16 volumes published by Butler--four of which were for adults (Al Kaline and the Detroit Tigers, Abandon Ship!, Inferno! and Nature at War), the rest for juvenile readers--as well as Magnolia Plantation, an historical romance written under the pen name "Beverly Butler." The "Magazines" and "Newspapers" subseries contain a large albeit incomplete sampling of Butler's output in a variety of publications while the "Pulp Fiction" section highlights his contributions to detective and sports serials in the forties and fifties. Miscellaneous material is gathered in "Other."
  - Manuscripts
    - Copper Fever!, circa 1985 (Box 2)
    - Articles
      - "Al Kaline: Is He a Superstar?", 1973 (Box 2)
      - "The Girls You See on Vacation,", undated (Box 2)
      - "The Historical Charms of Bardstown,", circa 1991 (Box 2)
      - "How to Get Sick in Mexico Without Even Trying,", undated (Box 2)
      - Lincoln Heritage Trail article, 1977 (Box 2)
      - "Mackinac Island: Bermuda of the North,", circa 1980 (Box 2)
      - "Michigan's Mysterious Copper Mines,", undated (Box 2)
      - Outline of proposed article on Dayton AFB, undated (Box 2)
      - "Take a Tour of Tropical Texas,", 1976 (Box 2)
      - "Tequila: the Town and the Liquor,", undated (Box 2)
      - "The Town that Sees Red,", circa 1990 (Box 2)
      - "100 Years and Counting: Michigan's Grand Hotel,", circa 1987 (Box 2)
    - Other, circa 1967 (Box 2)
  - Books
    - Abandon Ship!, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Al Kaline and the Detroit Tigers, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Baseball's All-Star Game Thrills, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Baseball's Champion Pitchers, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Baseball's Most Valuable Players, 1977 (Box 2)
    - The Bob Allison Story, 1967 (Box 2)
    - The Harmon Killebrew Story, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Inferno!, 1975 (Box 2)
    - Magnolia Plantation, 1981 (Box 2)
      (written as Beverly Butler)
    - Millions of Cars, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Nature at War, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Roar of the Road, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Sports Heroes Who Wouldn't Quit, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Stormin' Norman Cash, 1968 (Box 3)
    - There's Nothing New in Sports, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Underdogs of Sport, 1969 (Box 3)
    - The Willie Horton Story, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Magazines
    - Adventure Road, 1986-1992 (Box 3)
    - Argosy, 1959-1963 (Box 3)
    - Carte Blanche, 1977-1979 (Box 3)
    - Chevron USA, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Climax, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Coronet, 1958-1965 (Box 3)
    - Discovery, 1976-1978 (Box 3)
    - Ford Times, 1959-1987 (Box 3)
    - Home & Away, 1981-1990 (Box 4)
    - Man to Man, 1950 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Living, 1979-1988 (Box 4)
    - Panorama, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Pro Football Stars, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Saga, 1960 (Box 4)
    - Saturday Evening Post, 1955 (Box 4)
    - See, 1960 (Box 4)
    - Sport, 1956-1958 (Box 4)
    - Travel/Holiday, 1979-1987 (Box 4)
    - Travel & Leisure, 1976-1982 (Box 4)
    - True, 1959-1974 (Box 4)
    - Other, 1952-1987 (Box 4)
  - Newspapers (Box 5)
    - Boston Globe, 1987-1990 (Box 5)
    - Chicago Tribune, 1976-1983 (Box 5)
    - Dallas Morning News, 1986-1990 (Box 5)
    - Detroit Free Press, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Detroit News, 1975; 1986 (Box 5)
    - Kansas City Star, 1978 (Box 5)
    - San Diego Union, 1981-1986 (Box 5)
    - South Bend Tribune, 1981-1990 (Box 5)
    - Other, 1989-1991 (Box 5)
  - Pulp Fiction
    - Best Sports, 1948 (Box 5)
    - Black Book Detective, 1948 (Box 5)
    - Black Book Detective, 1951 (Box 5)
    - Complete Sports, 1951 (Box 5)
    - Complete Sports, March 1954 (Box 5)
    - Complete Sports, October 1954 (Box 5)
    - Crack Detective and Mystery Stories, 1956 (Box 5)
    - Detective Novel Magazine, 1947 (Box 5)
    - Exciting Sports, 1947 (Box 5)
    - Famous Detective Stories, 1956 (Box 5)
    - FBI Detective Stories, 1949 (Box 5)
    - FBI Detective Stories, 1950 (Box 5)
    - Popular Sports Magazine, 1947 (Box 5)
    - Private Detective Stories, May 1948 (Box 5)
    - Private Detective Stories, November 1948 (Box 5)
    - Private Detective Stories, February 1949 (Box 5)
    - Private Detective Stories, April 1949 (Box 5)
    - Private Detective Stories, 1950 (Box 5)
    - Smashing Detective Stories, 1956 (Box 5)
    - Super Detective, 1948 (Box 5)
    - Super Detective, March 1949 (Box 5)
    - Super Detective, December 1949 (Box 5)
    - Street and Smith's Detective Story Magazine, 1947 (Box 6)
    - Super Sports, 1952 (Box 6)
    - Thrilling Detective, July 1946 (Box 6)
    - Thrilling Detective, October 1946 (Box 6)
  - Other
    - "The Gertrude Ederle Story,", 1975; audiocassette (Box 6)
    - "Jackie Robinson,", 2001 (Box 6)
      (excerpt from Journeys of Faith)
    - "The Mt. Hope Story: 1889-1989", circa 1989 (Box 6)
    - Page Proofs, 1962-1986 (Box 6)
    - Rand McNally Vacation and Travel Guide, 1977 (Box 6)
- Eleanor Butler
  The Eleanor Butler series contains materials created and compiled by Hal Butler's wife. Her diaries detail daily and significant events for a majority of the years 1936-1955 and her scrapbook collects clippings, correspondence, and keepsakes from her years as a student at Detroit's Central High School. Eleanor Butler was also active in the Zeta Tau Alpha Detroit Area Mothers Club and this series includes its organizational records (bylaws, correspondence, meeting minutes, etc.) as well as a scrapbook related to club events.
  - Diaries
    - 1936-1937 (Box 6)
    - 1942-1943 (Box 6)
    - 1946-1950 (Box 6)
    - 1951-1955 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook, 1930-1933 (Box 6)
    (originally in one album)
  - Zeta Tau Alpha Detroit Area Mothers Club Records: includes bylaws, correspondence, meeting minutes, etc., 1947-1968 (Box 6)
  - Zeta Tau Alpha Detroit Area Mothers Club Scrapbook, 1945-1970 (Volume 1)